是, 大臣  第3季第5集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:otherbreath 校对&时间轴:tpring
如坐针毡
你确定哈克是最佳人选吗?
Are you sure Hacker's the man for this?
是的
Yes.
他是制定国民综合交通政策的最佳人选?
He's the best choice to bring in an integrated transport policy?
是的      但他根本不懂交通
Yes. But he knows nothing about it!
没错
No.
你问过交通部长了吗?
You've sounded out the Transport Secretary
他坚决不干
He won't touch it.
确实 如坐针毡啊
Yes. This could turn out to be a bed of nails.
是顶荆冠
A crown of thorns.
是个圈套
A booby trap.
而且 还得看起来会有成就
It has to look like something抯 gong to be done.
需要一系列特殊才干
It calls for a particular combination of talents,
专搞徒劳无功这一套
lots of activity but no actual achievement.
我懂了
I see.
那就非哈克莫属了
Then Hacker is the man!
那我们怎么劝他?
So how do we go about him?
你是首相的首席特别顾问 你知道规则
You're the PM's Chief Special Advisor. You know the form.
把它弄成特殊荣誉
We make it seem like a special honour.
一个晋升 一份礼物
A promotion. A present.
但汉弗莱爵士会警告哈克万万接不得
But Sir Humphrey will tell Hacker he'd be crazy to do it.
是啊 "Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes"
Yes. Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes,
我知道他要说什么
I can hear him say.
可以译为 "小心希腊人的糖衣炮弹"
"Beware of Greeks bearing gifts," roughly translated.
汉弗莱还得给哈克译成英文
Humphrey would have put it in English for Hacker's benefit.
哈克上的伦敦政治经济学院
Hacker went to the LSE.
我也是      哦 我很抱歉
So did I. Oh, I am sorry.
我们必须立刻委任哈克
We must get an immediate commitment from Hacker
不给他机会通知汉弗莱
before he talks to Humphrey.
今天? 现在?      你觉得不管用?
Today? Now Don't you think it抣l work?
奉承一个政客? 几时失败过?
Flattering a politician? When's it ever failed?
我们叫它"交通总管" 怎样?
We'll offer to call him Transport Supremo, shall we?
不错 比交通冤大头好听多了
Yes, much more attractive than Transport Muggins!
啊 吉姆
Ah, Jim!
你好 马克
Hello, Mark.
阿诺德      喝点什么?
Arnold. Drink?
好的 谢谢
Yes, thank you.
一切都顺利吧?      很不错
Everything all right? Everything抯 fine.
我们想...
We wanted...
呃 是首相希望
That is, the Prime Minister wanted
内阁秘书和我
the Cabinet Secretary and me
问你点事...
to sound you out about something...
很大的荣誉 告诉你
something of an honour, I may say.
荣誉? 不是要...把我踢到上院去吧?
Honour? You don't mean kicked up there?
不 是真正的荣誉
No, no. A real honour.
要增加很大责任
A significant increase of responsibility.
请问 你怎么看
Now, what are your views
国民综合交通政策?
on the integrated National Transport Policy?
我...
Er... I... I...
那个 我...
Well, er... I...
请继续
Go on.
首相认为我们急需综合交通政策
The PM has decided we need a national transport policy.
是啊 为什么不呢?
Yes. Well. Why not?
你赞成?
You're in favour?
不幸的是 公众对国民交通业的不满
Public dissatisfaction with the nationalised transport industries
已经高调到使政府为难了 你知道的
Is now to worry the government, as you know.
请继续?
Can you go on?
不 继续不下去了      不 需要有个政策
No, we can't go on, not like this. We need a policy.
不能年年秋冬季骂管理层
Not just blame the management if there's an R in the month
春夏骂工会
and the unions the rest of the time.
不幸的是 它们汇到一起了
Unfortunately, they've got together.
现在一年四季都骂政府
Their line is It's the government's fault.
这种混乱都源于缺少综合政策
Everything wrong is not having an integrated policy.
我们提过政策啊      有吗?
We did have a policy before. Did we?
是啊 我们的政策就是没有政策
Yes, it was our policy not to have a policy.
但现在首相想要个积极政策
Well, now the PM wants a positive policy.
哦 首相 是啊
Oh, the PM. Yes, well, er...
我完全同意 我一贯这么认为
I couldn't agree more. I've always thought so.
很好
Good.
可这是交通部的事吧?
Surely it抯 a Ministry of Transport matter?
不
No.
交通部长当然很想插手
Obviously the Transport Secretary would love the job,
但他太贴近这行了
but he's too close to it all.
当局者迷      需要一个开明崭新的头脑
It needs an open mind, uncluttered.
所以 首相决定委任一名总管
So the PM has decided to appoint a supremo
来制订和执行国民综合交通政策
to develop and implement a national transport policy.
总管?     总管
Supremo? A supremo.
就是...
And...
完全正确
Exactly.
我们一致认为你最开明
It was agreed you had the most open mind.
并且毫无成见
And the most uncluttered.
当然 这也是很大的荣誉和责任
Of course it抯 a great honour and a responsibility.
可有什么 什么样的...我是说...
Er, but what... What sort of... Er... I mean...
你想问综合交通政策有何要求 是吗大臣?
what is required of an transport policy minister?
旨在帮助消费者      也很受公众拥戴
it抯 to help the consumer. Very popular with the public.
不是说它...      当然不 这是我的职责
Not that that would... No, of course not. it抯 my duty.
比如 高速公路的规划没顾及铁路
The motorways were planned without reference to the railways,
所以很多公路
so there are great stretches of motorway
跟已有铁路线并行
running alongside already existing railways.
而有些地区两样都没有      对 就知道你明白
While other areas aren't served at all. Quite.
还真挺简单的      是啊
it抯 really quite simple. Yes.
还有联运客票的问题      联运客票?
Then there's through tickets. Through tickets?
如果你想在亨里和伦敦间往返
If you want to commute from Henley to the City,
得买张火车票到帕丁顿
you need one British Rail ticket to Paddington
再买张地铁票到银行
and then an Underground ticket to the Bank.
你有没有见过
Have you ever seen
公交铁路综合时刻表?
a combined bus and railway timetable?
或铁路站台上的公交时刻表?
Or ever seen a bus timetable in a railway station?
公交车司机见过公交时刻表么?
Has a bus driver ever seen a bus timetable?
有条铁路西线 经过
There's a British Rail Western Region line
希思罗机场以北不到一里
running less than a mile north of Heathrow,
但却没有连通
but no link line.
整个伦敦 公交和铁路都没有整合
Bus and train services don't connect, all over London.
伦敦以外也是一样
And outside London there are problems.
可能吧 但我们不关心
Probably. But we don't know about them.
是啊 有很多余地啊
It's full of possibilities.
能让我先和汉弗莱商量一下吗?
You'd like me to discuss it with Humphrey and come back?
确实应该和汉弗莱爵士商量
There is much to discuss with Sir Humphrey,
但我们希望你马上表态
but we need an indication of your response now.
首相30分钟内就要去机场
The PM's car leaves for the airport in 30 minutes.
参加渥太华会议
The Ottawa conference.
还有纽约联合国总部演说      华盛顿会议
Then the UN speech in New York. Then Washington.
天 真是长途 谁来管这个国家呢?
Gosh, what a long trip. Who's gong to run the country
对不起 阿诺德 我真蠢
Sorry, Arnold. Silly question.
那我们给首相报喜了?      很多事要着手了
So we can give the PM the good news? There's a lot to put in hand.
好的 我接受      了不起 再来一杯吧
Oh, yes. I'm on. Splendid! Have another drink.
啊 大臣      抱歉我迟到了
Ah, Minister. Sorry I'm late.
我有个振奋人心的好消息      是什么 大臣?
Got some splendid news. Indeed, Minister?
我得到份新工作      本部门对失去您十分惋惜
I have a new job. The department will be sorry to lose you.
不 我是说额外工作
No, I mean an extra job.
要我制订
I've been asked to develop
国民综合交通政策 首相指派的
an integrated national transport policy by the Prime Minister.
知道了 那好消息是?
I see. And what was the good news?
这就是好消息啊
That was the good news.
哦 请原谅我冒失的提问
Oh. Then how, if I may be so bold as to enquire,
您如何定义坏消息?      什么?
would you describe bad news? What?
大臣 您知道接受这工作 后果会如何吗?
Do you realise what this job would mean if you accept it?
我已经接受了      您说什么?
I have accepted it. You've what?
我已经接受了      大臣 您开玩笑吧
I have accepted it. Minister, you're not serious!
对 这是荣誉 我们也确实需要交通政策
Yes, it抯 an honour. We need a transport policy.
如果您的"我们"是指英国 的确如此
If by 搘e?you mean Britain, that's quite true.
但如果"我们"是指我们部
But if by 搘e?you mean this department,
制订交通政策就像在我们颅骨上钻洞
we need a transport policy like an aperture in the cranial cavity!
吃力不讨好的事
It is a bed of nails!
我知道会有额外的行政工作 汉弗莱
I know it may cause extra administrative duties.
大臣 这不是重点
Minister, that is not the point.
之所以没有综合交通政策 是因为
The reason there's no integrated transport policy
它会有益于所有人 只除了制订它的大臣
In everybody's interest except the minister
为什么?
Why?
我怎样解释您好懂呢?
How can I put it in a manner which is close to your heart?
这是选票杀手      选票杀手?
It is the ultimate vote loser. Vote loser?
您觉得为什么交通部长不自己干?
Why do you think the Transport Secretary isn抰 doling it?
他为何推荐掌玺大臣?
Why did he suggest the Lord Privy Seal?
为什么掌玺大臣又推荐
Why did the Lord Privy Seal suggest
兰开斯特公爵郡大臣
the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster,
他又为何推荐枢密院长?
who suggested the President of the Council?
我没听说啊
I didn抰 know this.
为什么他们请您去10号 要瞒着我呢?
And why did they invite you to No. 10 behind my back?
大臣 这一苦差在整个白厅
This hideous appointment has been hurtling round Whitehall
被踢来踢去三个星期 完全是颗未爆弹
for three weeks like a grenade with the pin taken out!
如果被我拿下 我会荣耀加身
If I pull it off, It'll be a feather in my cap.
如果您拿下来 大臣 就加不了身了
If you pull it off, Minister, It won抰 be in your cap any more.
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard.
如果您真的拿下 十年内不会有人受益
If you pull it off, no one will feel the benefits for ten years.
远在那之前 您和我就不在职了
Long before that, you and I will have moved on.
升职了
Or up.
更可能离职了      离职?
Or out. Out?
眼下 制订政策意味着做决策
In the meantime, formulating policy means making choices.
而做决策 只会取悦受惠的人
Once you do that, you please the people that you favour,
但激怒其他所有人
but infuriate everybody else.
赢得一票 就丢掉十票
One vote gained, ten lost.
如果您把一份工作给公路局
If you give the job to the road services,
铁路局和工会都要抗议
the rail board and unions will scream.
给铁路局 公路局会把您大卸八块
Give it to the railways, the road lobby will massacre you.
削减英航的投资计划
Cut British Airways Investment plans,
他们当天下午就会召开记者会
they'll hold a devastating press conference that same day.
但我会成为交通总管啊
But I'm gong to be Transport Supremo!
似乎公务员术语是交通冤大头
I believe the Civil Service vernacular Is Transport Muggins!
不 汉弗莱 是首相让我
No, the Prime Minister has asked me
接受这份工作 担起责任
to undertake this task, this necessary duty.
无论如何 我们都要尽职尽责
After all, we must all endeavour to do our duty.
而且 马克爵士认为会招揽选票
Furthermore, Sir Mark thinks there may be votes in it.
好东西我不会挑嘴的
I won't look a gift horse in the mouth.
大臣 您挑的是特洛伊木马的嘴
You're looking a Trojan horse in the mouth!
如果仔细看这马 会看见特洛伊人吗?
If we look closely at this gift horse we'll find it full of Trojans?
如果朝特洛伊木马嘴里看 大臣
If you'd looked a Trojan horse in the mouth,
里面会是希腊人
you'd have found Greeks inside.
是希腊人送特洛伊木马给特洛伊人的
It was the Greeks who gave the Trojan horse to the Trojans.
理论上这不是特洛伊木马 是希腊木马
Technically, it wasn抰 a Trojan horse but a Greek horse.
因此 名言"Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes"
Hence the tag Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes,
您记得的
which, you'll recall,
经常会错误的翻译成
Is usually and somewhat Inaccurately translated,
"小心希腊人的糖衣炮弹"
"Beware Greeks bearing gifts,"
如果您没上伦敦政经大学 您一定记得
or you would recalled had you not attended the LSE.
希腊谚语很好 但我们能否不要跑题?
Greek tags are all very well, but can we stick to the point?
对      抱歉 希腊谚语?
Yes... Sorry, Greek tags?
"小心希腊人的糖衣炮弹"
"Beware Greeks bearing gifts."
欧共体一定会说成
The EEC equivalent would be,
"小心希腊人的橄榄油炮弹"
"Beware Greeks bearing an olive oil surplus"!
绝妙      不 大臣 关键问题是
Excellent. No, the point is, Minister,
正如特洛伊木马来自希腊
just as the Trojan horse was Greek,
您说的希腊谚语 其实源自拉丁
what you call a Greek tag Is, in fact, Latin.
显然 希腊人绝对不会提防自己人
The Greeks wouldn't suggest bewaring of themselves,
如果可以用这样的分词
if one can use such a participle,
之所以是拉丁 不仅因为"Timeo"以"o"结尾
and it抯 clearly Latin not because "Timeo" ends in "o",
希腊语第一人称也以"o"结尾
as the Greek first person also ends in "o".
尽管希腊语里有"Timao"这个词 意为"我荣幸"
No, there is a Greek word "Timao" meaning "I honour",
但"os"是一个单数主格词尾
but the "os" ending is a nominative singular termination
希腊语第二变位 拉丁语中则是宾格复数
of a second declension in Greek and an accusative plural in Latin,
尽管Danaos不仅是希腊语中的"希腊"
though actually Danaos Is not only the Greek for Greek,
也是拉丁语中的"希腊" 挺有意思的
It's also the Latin for Greek.
我明白了 汉弗莱 但真那么糟糕吗?
Yes, I take your point, Humphrey, but is it really as bad as that?
大臣 也许...
Minister, perhaps...
也许我该为您证明一下
Perhaps you will allow me to prove it to you.
我会安排一次预备会议
I will arrange a preliminary conference for you
召集三位副秘书 分别来自交通部的
with three Under-Secretaries from the Department of Transport,
公路 铁路和航空部门
from the roads, rail and air transport divisions.
公务员? 这能证明什么?
What will that prove?
会列举一些您将面临的问题
It may illustrate some problems you will encounter.
也许你是对的 汉弗莱
You may be right.
但如果我成功了 这将成为我的马岛大捷
But if I succeed, this could be my Falkland Islands.
对
Yes.
您会成为加尔铁里将军
And you could be General Galtieri!
无意冒犯 大臣 我不得不指出
With respect, I feel constrained to point out
这个议案原则不对
the proposal is deeply misguided.
哦 你的意见是?      我建议 政府应该
So what do you suggest? It should be government policy
把公路作为货运的重点手段
to designate road haulage as freight transport.
抱歉打断一下 大臣
If I might crave your indulgence for a moment,
我认为这种政策 坦率地说
I think such a policy would be, not to put too fine a point on it,
太目光短浅了
unacceptably short-sighted.
铁路才是最佳运输手段
Rail transport must surely be the favoured carrier
健全的政府都会这么想
under any sane national policy.
恕我直言
With the greatest respect,
二位的议案都会酿成大祸
both those proposals are formulae for disaster.
从长远考虑 应加强空运建设
Long-term considerations mandate the increase of airfreight.
如果大臣希望预算大规模上升...
If the minister wants a massive budget increase...
如果大臣接受长期而坚决的铁路大罢工...
If the minister accepts a long, bitter rail strike...
如果大臣能容忍公众不满情绪突然上涨...
If the minister can tolerate a massive rise in public discontent...
等一下
Hold on!
我们代表政府 不是吗?      您当然是 大臣
We are the government, aren抰 we? Indeed you are, Minister.
所以我们利益一致      当然 毫无疑问
So we're all on the same side. Indeed, no question.
都为了国家好
Doling what's best for Britain.
难道毁灭航空业是为国家好?
Is the end of the airfreight business best for Britain?
国家怎能承受铁路四分五裂?
How is Britain served by the destruction of the railways?
显然 公路衰退又怎会有益于国家呢?
How does Britain benefit from a deterioration of the road network?
我是要整个政府的货运政策
I want options for the government's freight transport
我以为这个预备会议
I thought a preliminary discussion,
是老朋友围在一起 提些积极意见...
a few friends around the table, a few positive suggestions...
当然 扩充铁路系统...      壮大高速公路...
An expansion of rail... expansion of motorway...
提高空运能力...      我只想缩减预算
An expansion of airfreight. I need a reduction in costs.
如此一来 就只有一个办法
Then there is only one possible course.
的确如此
Indeed there is.
至于是什么也毋庸置疑
And there's no doubt what it is.
好极了 我喜欢最终达成共识
I always like to end on a note of agreement.
谢谢各位
Thank you, gentlemen.
大臣
Minister.
得安排下次会议时间 这边请
Perhaps we could discuss a date for our next meeting.
真是个直率的会议
That was a very frank meeting.
比直率更甚 大臣 简直刀光剑影了
More than frank, Minister. Frank bordering on direct.
没事 明早清洁工会把血迹擦掉的
The cleaners will mop up the blood tomorrow.
伯纳 能帮帮我吗?
Bernard, can you help me?
怎么帮 大臣?      副秘书也是公务员吧
How, Minister? Under-Secretaries are civil servants.
但他们却像律师 像公交利益集团雇来
But they behave like counsel briefed by the transport interests
打击政府的
to defeat the government.
很对 大臣      不 伯纳 这不对
That's right. No, Bernard, that's wrong.
但公务员原理如此
That's how it works.
一个部门管着谁 就由谁说了算
Controlled by the people it抯 supposed to control.
怎么讲?
How do you mean?
我们为何实行素质教育?
Why do we have comprehensive education?
谁乐意? 学生还是家长?      都不是
Who wanted it? Pupils, parents? Not really.
是全国教师协会
The National Union of Teachers,
它们是教育部的最大客户
the chief client of the Department of Education,
于是教育部就实施素质教育
so the DES went comprehensive.
您看 各部门都服务于
Departments act for the powerful interest
和它有永久关系的集团
with whom they have a permanent relationship.
就业部服务于劳工联合会
The Department of Employment lobbies for the TUC.
工业部服务于雇主 很完美的平衡
The Department of Industry lobbies for the employers.
能源部服务于石油公司
Energy lobbies for oil companies,
国防部为军队 内务部为警察
Defence for the armed forces, the Home Office for the police.
整个系统都在阻止内阁提出政策?
So the system alms to stop the Cabinet carrying out its policies?
总有人负责这个
Well, somebody's got to!
所以出台国民交通政策
So formulating a national transport policy
不仅要对抗交通行业
means fighting not just the transport industry
还有所有公务员?
but the entire Civil Servlce as well?
公务员不是该帮助政府施政吗?
Shouldn't the Civil Servlce help the government?
这个 只有当政策可行的时候
Well, as long as the government's wishes are practicable.
什么意思?
Meaning?
只有公务员认可的时候
As long as the Civil Servlce agrees with them!
有建树的会议 大臣
Useful meeting, Minister.
好吧 汉弗莱
All right, Humphrey.
你赢了
You win.
我赢了什么?      我们得赶紧脱身
What do I win? We must get out of our commitments.
很明显 交通总管头衔还是不要的好
Clearly the title Transport Supremo Is not worth having.
我们得让首相改变主意
We must change the Prime Minister's mind.
您的"我们"是复数
Is that "we" plural,
还是单指总管大人一人?
or do supremos now use the royal pronoun?
我说咱们俩 汉弗莱
I mean both of us, Humphrey,
除非你想行政部来负责
unless you want the DAA saddled with this.
那您的意思是?
So, what are you suggesting?
伯纳 能找到首相选区的地图吗
Bernard, find a map of the PM's constituency.
汉弗莱 我需要些建议      什么 大臣?
Humphrey, I need some advice. Yes, Minister?
你觉得一项国民交通政策
Could the formulation of a national transport policy
会不会被当地所反对?
have unwanted local repercussions?
会的 当然 大臣
Er, yes, indeed, Minister.
就算这选区的代表
Even in a constituency represented
是政府高级领导人
by a very senior member of the government,
实际上 是最高领导人?
the most senior member of the government?
真难堪 太难堪了
Deeply embarrassing!
大臣 这是街道图和指南
Here's the street map and the directory.
好极了 伯纳
Splendid.
这是首相的选区 是吧?
This is the Prime Minister's constituency, isn抰 it?
看 一个公园
Oh, look, a park!
挨着火车站
Near the station.
大臣 交通政策要件之一
One requirement of a transport policy
就是让公交站靠近火车站
Is to bring bus stations nearer to railway stations.
那就得建在公园里
But that would mean building on the park.
唉 是的
Alas, yes.
总得有人为国家利益做出牺牲
Somebody has to suffer in the national interest.
记下来 伯纳
Take a note, Bernard.
公交车站搬进夏洛特公园
Bus station to be moved into Queen Charlotte's Park.
大臣 这儿有个大型公交维修站
Oh, Minister, there's a big bus repair shop.
把公交和铁路维修站合并会更划算吧?
Isn't it economic to amalgamate the bus and train repairs?
当然 省不少钱呢
Absolutely. Big saving.
关闭公交维修站 伯纳
Bus repair shop to be closed, Bernard.
这是个通勤的国家 该怎么办?
This is commuter country, what about that?
通勤列车常年亏损
Commuter trains run at a loss.
只有上下班高峰期有人坐
They're only really used at rush hours.
所以通勤人员 实际上受了国家补助
So commuters are, in effect, subsidised.
这对别的人不公平吧?      令人发指 大臣
Isn't that unfair on the others? it抯 a great injustice.
通勤全部自费 伯纳
Commuters to pay full economic fares, Bernard.
当心 票价会翻一番
Mind, that'll double the price of tickets.
舍不得孩子套不着狼嘛
Can't make an omelette without breaking eggs!
这里火车站挺多的
There are quite a few railway stations in this area.
铁路和地铁都有      怎么?
British Rail and Underground. Yes?
有人说有夜间铁路服务的地区
One view is that areas with reasonable rail services
就不需要夜班公交了
don't need an evening bus servlce too.
言之有理 正合我意
Avery persuasive view, to my mind.
所有公交下午6点半收班
All bus services to cease after6.30pm.
那这块地方
What about this space
公交站原址怎么办?
when the bus station抯 moved to the park?
大臣 这个地区很缺集装箱卡车停车场
Well, the area's very short of parking space for container lorries...
尤其是晚上
especially at night.
公交站原址建集装箱卡车停车场 伯纳
Container lorry park on bus station site, Bernard.
进出道路要扩宽吧?
Won't that mean widening this access road?
没错
Yes, indeed.
室内游泳池西翼要拆掉了
We'll have to take away the western half of the swimming baths.
恐怕是这样
I'm afraid so.
当然 这就是一国之策对当地的影响
These are just the local implications of a broad national policy.
一点不错 大臣
Exactly, Minister.
不过 我还是该向首相打份私人报告
Even so, I ought to write a paper to the Prime Minister personally.
他一定想知道选区的变化
He'd like to know the constituency implications.
作为忠诚的内阁成员
As a loyal Cabinet member,
我有责任通知首相...和别的事一样
I owe that to the PM amongst other things!
但请注意 大臣 如果记者知道就糟了
Mind you, it would be awful if the press got hold of this.
牵扯到这么多城镇
With so many other boroughs threatened,
举国都会震惊的
there'd be a national outcry.
有没有被他们挖到消息的危险?
Is there a danger of them getting hold of it?
他们专会挖这种新闻
They're very clever at getting hold of things.
特别是复印件很多的时候      天啊
Especially if there are lots of copies. Oh, dear!
我应该给内阁同僚们发复印件
I shall have to make copies for my Cabinet colleagues.
他们的选区终究也会受影响的
Their own constituencies will be affected in due course.
如果泄露出去 这么多复印件
And if it were leaked, with so many copies,
没人会知道是谁泄的密
no one would ever discover who leaked it.
刚巧我今天午餐
It so happens I'm having lunch today
约了泰晤士报的麦克斯韦
with Peter Maxwell of The Times.
太棒了
Excellent!
别做我不会做的事
Don't do anything I wouldn't do.
请相信我 大臣
You can trust me, Minister!
你一定听到传闻了 彼得
I'm sure you've heard rumours, Peter,
这个综合交通政策
of this integrated transport policy.
陈词滥调又来了?      对 但这回很有趣
That old chestnut? Yes, but in an interesting form.
这个政策也许会有负面影响
The policy may have unwelcome side effects.
例如?
Such as?
合并公交铁路站造成的下岗问题
Job loss from integration of bus and rail terminals,
合并维修站的下岗问题
job loss from joint repair shops,
缩减公交和列车线路的下岗问题
job loss from streamlining of buses and trains,
减少班次 还是下岗问题
and reduction of services, causing job loss.
这只是开始
That's just for starters.
若真要提这个议案 可就轰动了
If this is being seriously proposed, It's quite a story.
对 比你想的还有趣 彼得      此话怎讲?
Even more interesting than you think. How's that?
受牵连最严重的
One of the areas to suffer most
是首相自己的选区
Is the Prime Minister's own constituency.
消息确切吗?
Have you any hard facts?
亲爱的彼得 问得真尖锐
Dear Peter, what a question!
报纸和政府可不一样 汉弗莱
Newspapers aren't like the government.
我们发表了声明 得证明它是真的
If we make statements, we have to prove them.
总有文件之类的吧? 公务员肯定有
Got something in writing? There always is in the Civil Servlce.
只有我们大臣写给首相的密函
Only a confidential note from my minister to the Prime Minister
还有他给内阁同僚们的22份类似函件
and a similar note to all 22 Cabinet colleagues.
哦 那就好
Oh, that's all right, then.
你要直接给我 还是让我找他们?
Will you show it to me or shall I get it from one of the others?
亲爱的彼得 这可是机密文件
Peter, it抯 a confidential document.
我泄露给任何人都属极度失职
It would be grossly improper of me to betray it to anyone
更不用说给记者了      的确
let alone a journalist. Of course.
你唯一拿到一份的机会
The only way you'd get hold of a copy
是有人误把它随处乱丢
Is if someone were to leave it lying around by mistake.
我明白了
I see.
哦 我回去干活了
Oh, well, back to the grindstone.
很高兴和你谈话 彼得 多谢你的午餐
Well, nice to talk, Peter. Thank you for the lunch.
谢谢      再见
Thank you. Goodbye.
哦 汉弗莱 你太大意了
Oh, Humphrey, you are so careless!
啊 吉姆 谢谢你过来
Ah, Jim. Thanks for dropping in.
我要先提醒你 首相很生气
I thought I ought to tell you that the PM isn抰 very pleased.
哦 生气?      很生气
Oh, not pleased? Not pleased.
上周二的泰晤士报      真可怕 我也生气
Last Tuesday's Times. Yes I'm not pleased either.
显然是泄密了      显而易见
There's obviously been a leak. Obviously.
内阁同僚都信不过了      什么意思?
Can't even trust Cabinet colleagues. What are you suggesting?
也可能不是他们
Well, it might not have been one of them.
我也送了份复本到10号
I sent a copy of my paper here to No. 10.
你们这儿不会泄密吧?
You don't think there's a leak here, do you?
首相办公室绝不会泄密      当然 别瞎想
The PM's office does not leak! Of course not. Perish the thought!
最烦的还不是泄密
It wasn抰 just the leak that was disturbing.
而是对议案内容的曲解
It was the misleading Implications of the proposals.
没有曲解 你读过我的报告吗?
No, not misleading. Have you read my paper?
你读过我的吗?
Have you read mine?
这是首相选区的报纸吧?
This is the paper from the PM's constituency.
似乎是的
I believe it is.
"首相干预并停止交通整顿议案"
"PM steps in to stop transport reorganisation proposals.
"选区的服务和就业受威胁的传闻"
Rumours that services and jobs were threatened
"今日已被粉碎"
in this constituency were scotched today.
"据悉 首相已将明确指示"
Apparently the PM has given a firm direction
"给予交通总管吉姆哈克"
to Transport Supremo designate Jim Hacker."
我没收到首相指示啊      现在收到了
I haven't heard from the PM. You have now!
恐怕这次泄密 途径暂且不论 确实是
I'm afraid this leak, wherever It comes from, is a verbatim report
首相从渥太华发布的秘密口令
of a confidential minute dictated by the PM in Ottawa.
所以 国民交通政策得重新考虑
So, the national transport policy will need some re-thinking!
这可难办了
It will be difficult.
首相认为当大臣的就得解决难题
The PM feels it抯 the difficult jobs that the ministers are there for,
如果他们还想当大臣
assuming they wish to remain as ministers.
是的 当然
Yes, well, of course.
如果需要...      重新考虑
If it needs, er... Rethinking.
重新考虑 那我就...再考虑
Rethinking, then of course I shall rethink.
很好
Good.
可首相选区的报纸怎么知道的?
But how did this get into the PM's own local paper?
不知道 但首相办公室绝不会泄密
I don't know. But the PM's office does not leak.
真可怕是吧? 如今谁都信不过了
Shocking, though, isn抰 it? You can't trust anyone nowadays.
回到了起点 这也不错
Back to square one. Well, that's all right.
什么不错 大错特错
It is not all right.
这死工作还在我头上
I'm still stuck with this ghastly job.
不 大臣 这是绝好的消息
No, Minister, it is excellent news.
我们现在出台另一种准议案
We now present our other kind of non-proposal.
哪一种?      高成本 高编制议案
What other kind? The high cost, high staff kind.
我们提议 设立全国交通管理局
We now propose a British National Transport Authority
结构完整 有地区分局 委员会
with a full structure, regional board, area council,
办事处 联络委员会 应有尽有
local office, liaison committee, the lot.
八万员工 每年十亿预算
80,000 staff, billion-a-year budget.
财政部肯定会绝倒
The Treasury will have a fit!
这烂摊子肯定会被踢回交通部
The whole thing will go back to the Department of Transport.
好极了 能帮我拟个草案吗 汉弗莱?
Great. Could you do me a paper on this, Humphrey,
编制 费用细节和一份年度预算
with full staff and costing details and a specimen annual budget?
首页有份简单摘要
There's a one-page summary on the front.
汉弗莱  你真了不起      不值一提 大臣
Humphrey, you're marvellous. it抯 nothing, really.
这要是被记者搞到手可如何是好
I say, what if the press should get hold of this!
又有一次泄密要调查了
They'd have to have another leak enquiry.
他们真的会调查吗?
Will they really set up an enquiry
一定会      不会很尴尬吗?
Bound to. Won't that be embarrassing?
不不 泄密调查就是为这个
No, no, no. That's what leak enquires are for.
做做样子 不会真的调查
Setting up. They don't actually conduct them.
也许会委派人员 但他们根本不见面
Members may be appointed, but they'll never meet,
更不会交报告了
and certainly never report.
伯纳 你记得几个揪出泄密者的调查?
How many leak enquires can you recall that named the culprit?
凑个整数      如果您要整数...
In round figures. If you want it in round figures...
零个      瞧 他们从不报告
None. They never report.
如果泄密的是公务员 揪出来就不公平
If the culprit is a civil servant, It'd be unfair to publish.
政客会担责任
Politicians take the rap.
如果是政客 也不能公开
If it抯 a politician, you can't publish
不然他会揭露其他同僚
or he抣l disclose other leaks by his colleagues.
但最重要的原因是
But chiefly they can't publish
多数泄密都来自10号
because most leaks come from No. 10.
只有国家这条船 伯纳
The ship of state, Bernard,
是从顶上漏水的
Is the only ship that leaks from the top.
所以 如果是首相口无遮拦
So, if the problem is a leaky PM,
就像这次 真相就难揭露了
as in this case, the facts are difficult to get at
更不会公开
and impossible to publish if you do!
提醒您 大臣 报社有位先生在等您
May I remind you, a gentleman from the press is waiting.
啊 是的      我先离开 大臣
Ah, yes. I'll leave you, Minister.
哦 汉弗莱...      大臣?
Oh, er, Humphrey... Minister?
你还有计划书的复本吗?
Have you got another copy of these new proposals?
当然
Of course!
给您      因为我非常健忘
There. Because I'm awfully absent-minded.
总把文件到处乱放...
I'm always leaving documents lying around...
之后就忘记放在哪了
forgetting where I've put them.
非常了解 大臣
I do understand, Minister!
又一个泄密 这次更加严重
Another leak. This is extremely serious.
是的 当然
Yes, indeed.
已经快到惩戒线了
This is almost approaching a disciplinary level.
完全同意 是吧汉弗莱?      当然 大臣
I so agree, don't you, Humphrey? Indeed, Minister.
能找到泄密者就好了
If only we could find the culprits.
事态确实极其严重
It would be a most serious matter.
也许我能帮忙
Perhaps I can help there.
我认为如果我用上自己的人脉
I think that if I were to use my influence,
就能揭露泰晤士报
I could achieve a disclosure from The Times
如何得到第一份计划的
of how they got hold of your original plan.
哦?      真的?
Oh? Really?
也许我也能帮忙      真的吗?
I might be able to help there, too. Indeed?
您确定吗 大臣?      当然
Are you sure, Minister? Oh, yes.
我有把握找出记者从哪得知
I'm confident I can find out where the press got the leak
首相对提案的异议的
about the PM's opposition to our plan.
如果查出是首相办公室泄露的
If it transpired the leak came from the Prime Minister's own office
会比内阁大臣办公室泄密更严重吧
that'd be serious than from a Minister's office.
我是说 光是安全问题...
I mean, the security implications alone...
也许应该派警察 或者军情局
Perhaps we should call in the police or MI5.
军情局 好主意 大臣
MI5, good idea, Minister.
首相办公室泄密 问题可严重了
A leak from the Prime Minister's office Is very serious.
不过 首先要调查第一次泄露的问题
our first priority must be the original leak.
不 首先要调查10号泄密的可能性
Surely we should first investigate a possible leak from No. 10.
无论如何 泄密已经导致全国哗然
In all events, the inevitable public outcry after all these leaks
我们行政部更难以制订
will make it awfully difficult for us to formulate
这份国民综合交通政策
an integrated national transport policy in the DAA.
时机尚未成熟 风声仍在盛传
The time is unripe, the cellmate is unsuitable.
大气候很不利
The atmosphere is unfavourable.
我们唯一的解决途径也行不通了
Our only avenues of approach are now blocked.
我在想...
I wonder...
是不是应该把整件事
If it might not be wiser to take the whole matter
交还交通部?
back to the Department of Transport?
这...阿诺德 真是明智      我怎么想不到
That, Arnold, is a brilliant idea. I wish I'd thought of that.
但泄密还没解决      当然
There remains the question of the leaks. Indeed.
我认为这事应该严肃处理
I feel we ought to treat this with the utmost gravity.
我想到个办法      是什么?
I think I have a solution. Indeed?
你们能向首相建议
Will we recommend to the Prime Minister
马上发起一次泄密调查吗?
that we set up an immediate leak enquiry
是 大臣
Yes, Minister!